so now we will look at so-called history
based predictors which are trying to do
well on things like when we have a not
taken taken not taken taken repeating
pattern or something like to not take
ins followed by a taken and then again
to not take ins followed by a taken etc
again it's a repeating pattern that even
a two bit predictor will miss predict
the taking branch so it's one-third miss
predicting and even more complicated
pattern based things it's important to
know that these are really 100%
predictable these are repeating patterns
once you figure out what the pattern is
the branch becomes 100% predictable it's
just that these branches are not
predictable
with simple and bit counters what we
need is a predictor that somehow learns
the pattern really and then it becomes a
very accurate predictor how do we learn
the pattern well we don't just look at
what the majority outcome here for
example here there is no majority
outcome at all here not-taken is the
majority outcome but Takens happen very
frequently so if we just look at what's
the majority behavior we'll have a lot
of mispredictions what we want to look
at is the so-called history of the
branch what were the latest so many
outcomes for example if we have the not
taken taken not taken taken and so on
behavior let's ignore the first one for
now and look at this particular
prediction here what we know is that the
previous outcome was not taken and if we
know what the pattern is then we know
that when the branch has been not taken
previously our prediction should be
taken and then here the history says the
branch previously was taken so our
prediction should be not taken and if
you're doing it this way then you will
be predicting correctly every single
time so what we need to learn is that
under the history of not taken our
decision should be taken under the
history of taken our decision should be
not taken let's now look at this
NNT branch
in that case we have not taken not taken
taken not taken not taken taken the
history now needs to consider the last
two decisions so when we see not taken
not taken we should be predicting taken
when we see not taken taken as the
previous two outcomes we should be
predicting not taken and when we see
taken not taken we should be predicting
not taken and then we're back to not
taking not taking history where we
should be predicting taken so if we
consider four different histories
different predictions then we will train
our predictor so that it for this
history predicts one outcome for this
history it predicts possibly another
outcome for this history predicts a
different outcome and so on and then
this becomes a very predictable branch